                    Republic of the Philippines
            DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR AND LOCAL GOVERNMENT
           DILG-NAPOLCOM Center, EDSA corner Quezon Avenue, West Triangle, Quezon City                     http://www.dilq.com.ph 
                     http://www.dilq.com.ph 


      8 March 2021



      HON. JIVY ROE C. BOMBEO 
      Vice-Mayor
      Kidapawan City, Cotabato



      Dear Vice-Mayor Bombeo:

         This is in reference to your letter dated 14 December 2020 requesting 
      this Department to declare Supplemental Budget No. 9 of Kidapawan City, 
      Cotabato as null and void on the grounds of illegality and for being ultra vires.
.
         As culled from your letter, on 17 August 2020, Mayor Evangelista 
      issued a notice of session scheduled on 18 August 2020 at 9:00 AM to 
      deliberate and approve his request for the approval of the proposed 
      Supplemental Budget No. 9 amounting to Twenty Million Four Hundred 
      Twenty Three Thousand Nine Hundred Forty and 121100 (Php 
      20,423,940.12) and authority to negotiate a loan of Php Two Hundred Forty 
      Two Million (Php 242,000,000) with any reputable government bank to 
      finance several projects of the city government.

         The said notice of session was received by your Office at 1:25 PM on 
      17 August 2020, without any attachment or any supporting document. On 
      the same day, Mayor Evangelista wrote another letter, bearing the same 
      content and tenor as the first one, but this time, the letter was marked with 
      bold underline stating "Certified Urgent".

         Your Office and the Secretary to the Sanggunian received a copy of 
      the said letter at around 2:55 PM on 17 August 2020 without any attachment 
      or any supporting document, specifically that of the proposed appropriation 
      ordinance authorizing Supplemental Budget No. 9 as well as the proposed 
      resolution authorizing the negotiation of a loan amounting to Php 242 million.

   On 17 August 2020, you issued a letter calling off the supposed special 
session dated 18 August 2020 for failure to comply with the rule that the 
notice of session must be submitted to the Presiding Officer at least one (1) 
day before intended session, as required by Section 52 (d) of the Local 
Government Code of 1991 and Article 105 (2) (ii) of its Implementing Rules 
and Regulations.

   Moreover, the session was also called off for lack of material time for 
the Secretary to the Sanggunian to prepare the Order of Business and the 
lack of necessary documents to support the same as mandated by Section 
1 of Rule VIII of the Internal Rules of Procedure (IRP).

   However, ten (10) members of the Sangguniang Panlungsod (SP) 
wrote a notice of session dated 19 August 2020 calling for a special session 
on 24 August 2020 at 9:0AM to deliberate and approve the same matters 
previously requested by Mayor Evangelista in his letter dated 17 August 
2020.

   The Sanggunian Panlungsod then proceeded to conduct a special 
session on 24 August 2020, wherein they unanimously agreed that the 
matter granting authority to the City Mayor to apply for a Php 242-million loan 
should be deferred. However, on the matter of ordinance approving 
Supplemental Budget No. 9, SP Member Ruby Padilla-Sison raised a point 
of order arguing, among others, that it was not proper for the Sanggunian to 
approve another supplemental budget as it would run contrary to Section 4 
of Appropriation Ordinance No. 20-008, which declared that no subsequent 
supplemental budget or any appropriation will be approved without 
complying with the weekly reportorial requirements on the release, utilization 
and disbursement of funds in relation to COVID-19 and the donations 
received by the city government during the calamity caused by earthquakes.

   It is worthy to note that on 24 July 2020, you wrote a letter addressed 
to the City Accountant, Gina Ong, demanding the latter to render a report of 
funding, liquidation and utilization of the funds disbursed under 
Supplemental Budget Nos. 1 to 8, series of 2020. But Mayor Evangelista 
sent his reply and only attached a general report ion the fund utilization and 
status of program implementation for the COVID-19 related projects for the 
month of July 31, 2020 and funded out of the BGCM and 20% Development 
Fund under Supplemental Budget No. 6.

    Moreover, on 23 September 2020, you wrote a letter addressed to 
 Mayor Evangelista requesting for the list of donors and the corresponding 
 amount of donations, as well as its utilization and liquidation, in connection 
 with the donations received by the City Government of Kidapawan in the 
 aftermath of the earthquake that struck the city. Ostensibly. no report on the 
 matter was rendered by the Office of the City Mayor.

   As such, you ruled that the request for the approval of Supplemental 
 Budget No. 9 is out of order.

   Apparently, immediately after the special session was adjourned, 
 eleven (11) SP members issued a notice of session calling for another 
 special session on 26 August 2020 at 9:00am, purportedly to deliberate and 
approve the same subject matter- the ordinance approving Supplemental 
 Budget No. 9, thereby disregarding your earlier ruling.

   However, said special session was called off in a Memorandum dated 
25 August 2020 issued by you, for failure to comply with the requirements of 
calling a special session. Moreso, the subject matter of the supposed special 
session has been declared out of order. Said Memorandum was addressed 
to and received by the SP members as well as SP Secretary Cabelin and 
other members of the Sanggunian Secretariat.

   Despite being duly notified of the memorandum calling off the said 
special session, SP members conducted the "hurried" session and swift 
passage and approval of Supplemental Budget No. 9 on 26 August 2020. 
The SP members deleted the reportorial requirements which supposedly 
mandate Mayor Evangelista to submit a weekly report to the Sanggunian 
regarding the utilization of the funds.

   Hence, the subject letter-request.

   Based on your representation, Supplemental Budget No. 9 on 26 
August 2020 was passed by the majority of the SP Members during the 
special session called for the purpose and thereafter, swiftly approved (we 
suppose, by the Mayor).

   Please be apprised that the Department is an agency under the 
executive branch of the government and as such, it has no authority to 
declare null and void any ordinance or resolution of the local sanggunian, or

any acts committed by the members thereof which is alleged to be a violation 
of the Local Government Code of 1991 or other applicable laws.

  Rather, RA 7160 or the Local Government Code of 1991 provides 
already a remedy or procedure to see to it that the ordinances or resolutions 
approving the local development plans and public investment program 
approved by a component city, like Kidapawan City, are within the powers 
conferred upon it, to wit:

   SECTION 56. Review of Component City and Municipal Ordinances or 
      Resolutions by the Sangguniang Panlalawigan. - (a) Within 
      three (3) days after approval, the secretary to the Sanqqunian 
      Panlungsod or Sangguniang bayan shall forward to the 
      Sanqqunianq Panlalawigan for review, copies of approved 
      ordinances and the resolutions approving the local development 
      plans and public invesiment programs formulated by the local 
      development councils.

      (b) Within thirty (30) days after receipt of copies of such ordinances 
        and resolutions, the Sangguniang Panlalawigan shall examine 
        the documents or transmit them to the provincial attorney, or if 
        there be none, to the provincial prosecutor for prompt 
        examination. The provincial attorney or provincial prosecutor 
        shall, within a period of ten (10) days from receipt of the 
        documents, inform the Sangguniang Panlalawigan in writing of 
        his comments or recommendations, which may be considered 
        by the Sangguniang Panlalawigan in making its decision.

      (c) If the Sanqqunianq Panlalawigan finds that such an 
        ordinance or resolution is beyond the power conferred 
        upon the Sangguniang Panlunqsod or Sangguniang bayan 
        concerned, it shall declare such ordinance or resolution 
        invalid in whole or in part. The Sangguniang Panlalawigan 
        shall enter its action in the minutes and shall advise the 
        corresponding city or municipal authorities of the action it 
        has taken.

      (d) If no action has been taken by the Sanqqunianq 
        Panlalawiqan within thirty (30) days after submission of 
        such an ordinance or resolution, the same shall be 
        presumed consistent with law and therefore valid.
             (Emphasis Supplied)


  If the Sangguniang Panlalawigan failed to take action on Supplemental 
Budget No. 9 within 30 days after submission or after review, the said august

body finds Supplemental Budget No. 9 consistent with law and therefore 
valid, the next remedy is for you to file appropriate action before the proper 
forum. Jurisprudence is replete of cases holding that "(A) municipal 
ordinance is not subject to collateral attack. Public policy forbids collateral 
impeachment of legislative acts."


  This opinion is being rendered without prejudice to any contrary 
opinion of competent authorities and the courts.


  We hope to have assisted you accordingly. Thank you.



                    Very truly yours,


              BY   ORITY OF THE SECRETARY:



                      NGAN, CESO III 
                     fficer-in-Charge
           Office of the Undersecretary for Local Government



LLLS/27/17 

Copy furnished:

  DIR. JOSEPHINE C. LEYSA
  Regional Director, DILG Region XII
  Prime Regional Government Center, Carpenter Hill 
  Koronadal City




















'San Miguel Brewery, Inc. vs. Magno (21 SCRA 293).

