               Republic of the Philippines
    DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR AND LOCAL GOVERNMENT
     DILG-NAPOLCOM Center, EDSA corner Quezon Avenue, West Triangle, Quezon City 
               http://www.dilg.com.ph 


3 March 2021



ATTY. JOHANNA MARIE B. BERMUDO 
Municipal Legal Officer
Office of the Municipal Legal Officer 
Municipality of Barotac Nuevo, Iloilo


Dear Atty. Bermudo:


This has reference to your letter dated 15 July 2020 addressed to Engr. 
Ariel O. Iglesia, then Regional Director, DILG Region VI, requesting for 
this Department’s opinion regarding the following:

     1. Whether or not the public hearing conducted for the 
      application of quarry permit was legitimate and proper; and

     2. What are the essential requisites that the barangay must 
       comply in order to have a valid public hearing?


In an opinion rendered by DILG Region VI1 dated 17 August 2020, it was 
opined that pursuant to Department of Environment and Natural 
Resources Administrative order No. 2010-21 (DENR DAO No. 2010-21), 
public hearing is not explicitly required before a quarry permit may be 
issued. However, public hearing may be required by the Province to which 
the Municipality belongs.


While we adhere to the aforementioned opinion, this Department deems 
it best to elaborate the foregoing.


Foremost, although Republic Act No. 7942, otherwise known as the 
“Philippine Mining Act of 1995”, did not specifically mention that a public 
hearing is necessary for applications for quarry permit, it is nonetheless 
imperative to note that for certain mining projects, an Environmental 
Impact Statement (EIS) is required for an Environmental Compliance 
Certificate (ECC) to be issued, which is necessary for the issuance of a 
quarry permit.


1 Regional Legal Opinion No. 24, Series of 2020

   In relation thereto, pursuant to DAO No. 2017-152, one (1) public 
hearing shall be conducted for projects requiring Environmental Impact 
Assessment (EIS), Programmatic Environmental Impact Statement 
(PEIS), Programmatic Environmental Performance Report and 
Management Plan (PERPMP) and EIS-based Environmental 
Performance Report and Management Plan (EPRMP). Further, item 2.1, 
Annex A of DENR EMB MC 005, states that Mining and Quarrying 
Projects are required to have an ECC before the grant of quarry permit.

Notices of the aforesaid hearing shall be posted in conspicuous places in 
the municipality and barangay where the project is proposed to be located 
at least 15 days prior to the scheduled hearing3. The EMB Office with 
jurisdiction over the processing of ECC application shall plan, initiate, and 
conduct the aforesaid hearing4. In the conduct thereof, efficient exchange 
of information and views between and among the project proponent, the 
EMB-DENR, relevant agencies, local government units (LGUs) and other 
stakeholders on the environmental impacts assessment, management 
and monitoring for proposed projects applying for an ECC shall be 
ensured5.

Thus, while we adhere to the opinion rendered by the Regional Office, it 
is our considered view that if the application for quarry permit falls on item 
2.1, Annex A of DENR EMB MC 005, where an EIC and ECC are required 
to be secured for areas covering more than 25 hectares, public hearing is 
necessary. And such hearing shall be conducted by the EMB office. 
Therefore, the participation of the concerned barangay concerns solely on 
the exchange of views regarding the environmental impact of the project. 
Otherwise, if the area covers not more than 5 hectares, the application for 
quarry permit shall be applied before the Provincial Governor/City Mayor 
through the Provincial/City Mining Regulatory Board. To reiterate, there is 
no explicit provision of law which requires a public hearing in the barangay 
for purposes of acquiring a quarry permit.

That being said, it is our considered view that there is no need for a 
barangay hearing to be conducted for the application of a quarry permit. 
However, if the area covered by the said application covers more than 25 
hectares wherein an EIS and ECC are required, a public hearing is 
necessary which shall be conducted by the EMB office. On the other hand, 
if the area covers only not more than 5 hectares, the Provincial 
Government has the discretion whether or not a hearing shall be

2 02 May 2017
3 Item No. 12.4, DAO No. 2017-15
4 Item No. 13.2, DAO No. 2017-15
5 Item No. 13.3, DAO No. 2017-15

conducted6. Despite the foregoing, any opposition regarding the 
application for quarry permit shall be filed directly before the Regional 
Office concerned or through any PENRO or CENRO concerned for filing 
in the Regional Office for purposes of its resolution by the Panel of 
Arbitrators.


This opinion is being rendered without prejudice to any contrary opinion  
of competent authorities and the courts.


We hope to have assisted you accordingly. Thank you.


Very truly yours,
By Authority of the Secretary:




 MARLO L. IRINGAN
  Officer-in-Charge
Office of the Undersecretary for Local Government




Legal/91

Copy furnished:

  DIRECTOR JUAN JOVIAN E. INGENIERO, CESO IV 
  Officer in Charge, DILG-Region VI
  6 Parola Street, Fort San Pedro
  Iloilo City



































6 Regional Legal Opinion No. 24, Series of 2020

