             Republic of the Philippines
     DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR AND LOCAL GOVERNMENT
     DILG-NAPOLCOM Center, EDSA corner Quezon Avenue, West Triangle, Quezon City 
              http://www.dilq.corn.ph 

1 March 2021


HON. EVANGELINE H. JUBAS 
Vice-Mayor
Kauswagan, Lanao del Norte


Dear Vice-Mayor Jubas:


   This has reference to your letter dated 17 December 2020 requesting 
this Department's opinion on various issues concerning the propriety of acts 
of the Sangguniang Bayan of Kauswagan, Province of Lanao del Norte.

   As can be culled from your letter and its attachments, the Sangguniang 
Bayan (SB) of Kauswagan, Lanao del Norte, thru its SB Committee on Laws, 
Rules, Ethics and Good Government passed a Resolution Recommending 
to the Local Chief Executive Hon. Rommel C. Arnado for the Suspension of 
Mr. Fortunato A. Densing, SB Secretary for not Submitting the Required 
Documents Requested by the HR Department.


   Ostensibly, prior to the passage of the aforesaid Resolution, the SB 
Committee on Laws, Rules, Ethics, Good Government and Public 
Accountability adopted Committee Report No. 093-2020 which 
recommended, among others, the preventive suspension of SB Secretary, 
Mr. Densing to help him comply with his lacking requirements.


   On 5 October 2020, Municipal Mayor, Rommel C. Arnado previously 
filed before the Civil Service Commission (CSC) Regional Office No. 10 a 
case against SB Secretary Densing for Gross Neglect of Duty, Grave 
Misconduct, being Notoriously Undesirable, Gross Insubordination, 
Discourtesy in the Course of Official Duties and Unprofessionalism.

   Meanwhile, it is also represented in the subject letter that Municipal 
Mayor Arnado in his burning desire to go after those who dared oppose him 
and through sheer vindictiveness filed a case before the Office of the 
Ombudsman — Mindanao for Estafa through Abuse of Confidence against

    Furthermore, the Department is proscribed by its internal rules as 
provided in DILG Memorandum Order No. 2010-021 to act on queries of the 
following kinds, to wit: xxx

   1. Those containing facts that are justifiable in nature. Justiciable 
     issues are those that require adjudication by the courts of law as 
     to who between the opposing parties have the better right over a 
     given controversy;

   2. Those presumptively valid acts; e.g., enacted ordinance, 
     consummated acts that already enjoy the presumption of 
     regularity on the part of the public officer concerned, and similar 
     instances;

   3. Those that are litis pendencia or pending litigation, except when 
     the court itself, requests for opinion. In the event that the opinion 
     has been rendered by the Department and its field officers without 
     knowledge or the information that a case involving the issues 
     raised in the query is pending in court, such opinion shall 
     automatically be deemed ineffective ; and

   4. Those that are cognizable by other agencies of the government."

   Be that as it may, the following provisions of law/principles are 
discussed to guide you and the either parties in your next course/s of action.

   On the first issue, the Department opined in DILG Legal Opinion No. 
05, series of 2020, citing DILG Legal Opinion No. 032-94, dated 02 March 
1994, that:

     "Relevantly, under Section 445 (a) of RA 7160, the municipal vice-mayor 
   shall 'appoint all officials and employees of the sangguniang bayan, except 
   those whose manner of appointment is specifically provided in this Code." 
   Considering that sanggunian employees are appointees of the vice-mayor, 
   they are, therefore, within the latter's administrative authority, as all their duties 
   and functions relate to services to be rendered in the sanggunian. It being so, 
   the imposition of disciplinary actions/measures against officials and employees 
   of the sanggunian are within the jurisdiction of the vice-mayor."

1 Supplemental to Memorandum Order No. 2010-01 dated 4 March 2010 (Request for Legal Opinion from the DILG 
Central Office)

you and your daughter Michelle Jubas Buhia. Apparently, the matter has 
been referred to the SB Committee on Laws which expeditiously 
recommended to the Office of Municipal Mayor Arnado on what 
penalty/grounds/ruling the latter can do for what disciplinary actions 
especially that the accused was an elected official.

   It would not be amiss to note that ostensibly, seven (7) out of the ten 
(10) members of the Sangguniang Bayan are staunched ally of the Municipal 
Mayor, while the three (3) remaining members composed the minority, as 
such Municipal Mayor Arnado has the majority of the SB members 
supporting his every proposal even if such is no longer within the bounds of 
the law.

   Hence, your request for this Department's opinion on the following 
queries, which we quoted in toto:

  1. Does the Sangguniang Bayan through the SB Committee on Laws 
   have the jurisdiction and/or authority to hear, investigate and 
   recommend the suspension of an appointive municipal official 
   such as the Secretary to the Sangguniang Bayan 1414his-partieu-lar 
   ease?

  2. Does the Sangguniang Bayan through the SB Committee on Laws 
   have the jurisdiction and/or authority to investigate, inquire and/or 
   recommend to the Municipal Mayor for the imposition of 
   penalty/grounds/ruling for disciplinary actions against an elective 
   municipal official such as the Municipal Vice-Mayor and Presiding 
   Officer of the Sangguniang Bayan in this particular case?; and

  3. [Whether or not] the Municipal Mayor is clothed with authority to 
   enforce any penalty/grounds/ruling for disciplinary actions 
   against an elective municipal official such as the Municipal Vice- 
   Mayor and Presiding Officer of the Sangguniang Bayan in this 
   particular case?


   We regret to inform you that we cannot render an opinion on the above- 
enumerated issues due to the pendency of issues with the Civil Service 
Commission vis-à-vis SB Secretary Densing and with the Office of the 
Ombudsman vis-a-vis your concerns. We might pre-empt the resolution of 
the issues by the aforestated bodies.

   As to the second and third issues, Section 61 of Republic Act No. 
7160 or the Local Government Code of 1991 enumerates the disciplining 
authority vis-a-vis erring elective official of the municipality such as the Vice- 
Mayor, thus:


     Section 61. Form and Filing of Administrative Complaints.—A verified
  complaint against any erring local elective official shall be prepared as follows:




   (b) A complaint against any elective official of a municipality shall be filed 
     before the Sangguniang Panlalawigan whose decision may be appealed 
     to the Office of the President; and




   This opinion is being rendered without prejudice to any contrary 
opinion of competent authorities and the courts.


   We hope to have assisted you accordingly.Thank you.


                     Very truly yours,

               BY AUTHORITY OF THE SECRETARY:



                       GAN, CESO III 
                    Officer-in-Charge
            Office of the Undersecretary for Local Government
LLLS/27/17

Copy furnished:

   DIRECTOR ARNEL M. AGABE 
   Regional Director, DILG-Region X 
   Masterson Ave., Upper Carmen 
   Cagayan de Oro City

