                        Republic of the Philippines
           DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR AND LOCAL GOVERNMENT
                     A. Francisco Gold Condominium II Bldg, EDSA 
                    corner Mapagmahal St., Diliman, Quezon City

        OFFOCE OF THE UNDERSEMETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT

                                        WIG OPliOtIN

                                            25 July 2008

      MAYOR JOEL AMADO A. D1ESTRO 
   I  Real, Quezon

      Dear Mayor Diestro,

         This has reference to your letter dated 11 April 2008 where the following sequence 
      of events are deducible, to wit:

         ➢ On 15 January 2008, you received a letter from Governor Nantes inviting you to a 
           meeting on 31 January to 1 February 2008 to be held at the Provincial Capitol, 
           Lucena city.
         • On 31 January 2008, the Secretary of the Office of the Mayor received a copy of 
           an enacted ordinance from the Sangguniang Bayan for your approval
         • On 14 February 2008, you vetoed the said ordinance particularly items 2 and 3 
           thereof and transmitted the veto message to the sanggunian on the same date.
         ➢ On 3 March 2008, the Sangguniang Bayan held that the veto on said items (1 and 
           2) is ineffectual as it was exercised beyond the ten (10) day period provided for 
           under Section 54 of RA 7160 (The Local Government Code).

         You take exception to this pronouncement contending that the ten (10) day 
      period should be reckoned from 4 February 2008, the period/date you reported back to 
      office (excluding February 2 and 3 which fell on Saturday and Sunday respectively) after 
     'your official transaction with Gov. Nantes since it was only on that date (February 4) 
     'where the enacted ordinance of the Sangguniang Bayan was presented to you for your 
      perusal and study. Thus, if properly reckoned from the aforementioned date (4 February 
      2008), the veto on items 2 and 3, as well as the transmission of the veto message on 14 
      February 2008, is well within the ten (10) day period as mandated under Section 54 of RA 
     17160, infra.
IjIII     As there is now an on going conflict of interpretation which may result in a 
      prolonged impasse and divisiveness between the Office of the Mayor and Sanggunian, 
      you now seek the Department's official stand on the matter

          Please be advised that the resolution of the issue before us hinges on the 
      reasonable interpretation of Section 54 of the Code (RA 7160) which provides, in part, viz:

             "Section 54, Approval of Ordinances. — (a) Every ordinance enacted by the 
          sangguniang panlalawigan, sangguniang panlugsod, or sangguniang bayan shall be 
          presented to the provincial governor or city or municipal mayor, as the case may 
          be. If the local chief executive concerned approves the same, he shall affix his 
          signature on each and every page thereof; otherwise, he shall veto it and return the 
          same with his objections to the sanggunian, which may proceed to reconsider the 
          same. The sanggunian concerned may override the veto of the local chief executive 
          by two-third (2/3) vote of all its members, thereby making the ordinance or 
          resolution effective for all legal intents and purposes.

             (b) The veto shall be communicated by the local chief executive concerned 
          to the sanggunian within fifteen (15) days in the case of a province, and ten (10) days 
          in the case of a city of a municipality; otherwise, the ordinance shall be deemed 
          approved as if he had signed it". (Underlining ours)

                       We, at once note, that the statute utilized the word "presented", past tense form

           of the word "present" which is defined by Webster Dictionary as an act "to bring or 

           ,introduce into the presence of someone". "Presentment", on the other hand, is the noun- 

           word form' of the same word (present) and is defined, likewise by Webster, as "the act of 

           presenting, to an authority a formal statement of a matter to be dealt with". Whether 

           verb or noun, therefore, the intent is unmistakable: to engender awareness on the part 

           of the person to whom someone or something is presented. In the case of Delos Reyes vs. 

           Sandiganbayan (281 SCRA 631), the Supreme Court held:



                                   "Contrary to petitioner's belief, the grant of the veto power confers 
                       authority beyond the simple mechanical act of signing an ordinance or resolution, 
                       as a requisite to its enforceability. Such power accords the local chief executive the 

                       discretion to sustain a resolution or ordinance in the first instance or to veto it and 
                       return it with his objections to the Sanggunian, which may proceed to reconsider 
                       the same. The Sanggunian concerned, however, may override the veto by a two- 
                       thirds (2/3) vote of all it members thereby making the ordinance or resolution 
                       effective for all legal intents and purposes. It is clear, therefore, that the 
                       concurrence of a local chief executive in the enactment of an ordinance or 
                       resolution, requires, not only a flourish of the pen, but the application of 
                       judgment after meticulous analysis and intelligence as well". (Emphasis Ours)



                       Congress arguably preferred the word "presented" from its equally known 

           Counterparts such as delivered or submitted, as the former is more conducive to do 

           homage or justice to that highlighted phrase in the above-cited decision.

           I'
                       When is presentment deemed made? Presentment is deemed fulfilled not only 

I          When a person is actually made aware of the presence of something or someone but so 

           also when he is presumed to be aware or ought to be aware of the same. For instance, 
1:1
           presentment to a secretary, whose official duty is to receive official communication, 

           documents and the like in the ordinary course of business — considered presentment to a 

           principal-employer if the latter is physically present and is thus in a position to receive 

           and make himself aware of said things. The• fact that he ultimately and deliberately 

        II ignored what was delivered to the secretary is no argument for the presumed 

           presentment that had already set in.
        ,
       I
              I        Reckoned by these considerations and applying the same in your case, we hold

           that a mere receipt by your Secretary of the enacted ordinance is not within the scope of 

           the concepts "presented" or "presentment" as it did not have the effect of placing or 

           putting you into a presumed awareness of the enacted ordinance. The reason for this is 

           that, when the enacted ordinance was officially received by your secretary, you were not 

           physically present on account of your meeting with the governor. Ergo, you could not be 

         I in position to make yourself aware of said enacted ordinance. That period came much

       :1 later, on 4 February 2008 to be exact, when you reported back for work. As this was the 

        1 date when the supposed enacted ordinance was presented or presumed presented to 

           you, it follows that the ten (10) day period within which to veto the said enacted 

           ordinance should rightfully be reckoned on this same even date. Applying the statutory 

           accepted rule in counting days — which is excluding the first day and including the last — 

           we note that the tenth day from 4 February 2008 is 14 February 2008. As the veto was

       1;1 ilrfade and communicated to the Sangguniang Bayan of Real Quezon on the said date (14 

           February 2008), we hold the view that the veto was validly made.



                       We hope we have enlightened you on the matter.







                                                                                                                     Very truly yours,


        1

                                                                                                               AUSTERE A. PANADERO 

                                                                                                     Undersecretary for Local Governm
   I 1

