                Republic of the Philippines
   DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR AND LOCAL GOVERNMENT
            A. Francisco Gold Condominium II Bldg, EDSA 
             corner Mapagmahal St., Diliman, Quezon City
   OFFICE OF THE UNDERSECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT

                                     10 July 2008


VICE-MAYOR ERNESTO S. MERCADO Olt.0 OPIN144  2.01:1L: 
Makati City


Dear Vice-Mayor Mercado:

    This has reference to your earlier letter seeking the Department's 
opinion relative to your proposed professionalization/standardization of 
Barangay Tanods in Makati City.

    Per your letter, Mayor Jejomar C. Binay of Makati City, in his desire 
to strengthen the maintenance of peace and order in that city, is planning 
to standardize all Barangay Tanods in their uniforms with paraphernalia, 
honoraria and other benefits as well as the trainings to be conducted with 
the end in view that they become professional Barangay Tanods in the 
thirty-three (33) component Barangays. Also, Mayor Binay is planning to 
adopt a common standard operating procedure to address the needs of his 
constituents on Public Safety and Peace and Order in a program to be 
known as the "Barangay Tanod Brigade of Makati City". According to you, 
the aforesaid project is based primarily on Section 16 of the Local 
Government Code of 1991 (RA 7160) pertaining to the "general welfare 
clause" and Executive Order No. 546 which authorizes the deputation of 
Barangay Tanods as force multipliers in the implementation of the peace 
and order plan in their area of responsibility.

     You also represented in your letter that each barangay in your city 
has already allocated funds but the same may not be sufficient so as to 
fully implement the project. For this reason, you are proposing that the city 
government will instead subsidize a portion of the funds needed so as to 
fully implement the project.

    In view of the foregoing, you are now seeking our legal opinion 
regarding your proposed project and whether it is possible for the city 
government of Makati to allocate funds to subsidize the honoraria, other 
benefits, uniforms and trainings of every barangay's roster of barangay 
tanods.

    In reply thereto, please be informed that we see no legal impediment 
in the execution of your proposed project. In fact, the following provisions 
under the Local Government Code of 1991, even sanction your proposed 
project of standardizing the Barangay Tanods in your city, to wit:

                                        - 2 -

              "SECTION 455. Chief Executive: Powers, Duties 
       and Compensatlon.—(a) The city mayor, as the chief 
       executive of the city government, shall exercise such 
       powers and perform such duties and functions as 
       provided by this Code and other laws.

              (b)    For efficient, effective and economical
       governance the purpose of which is the general welfare 
       of the city and its inhabitants pursuant to Section 16 of 
       this Code, the city mayor shall:

              (1) Exercise general supervision and control over 
       all programs, projects, services, and activities of the city 
       government, and in this connection, shall: xxx

              (2) Enforce all laws and ordinances relative to 
       the governance of the city and in the exercise of the 
       appropriate corporate powers provided for under Section 
       22 of this Code, implement all approved policies, 
       programs, projects, services and activities of the city 
       and, in addition to the foregoing, shall:

                     (1)    Ensure that the acts of the city's
              component Barangays and of its officials and 
              employees are within the cope of their prescribed 
              powers, duties and functions;"
                     xxx            xxx           xxx

       As to the issue on whether the city government of Makati may 
allocate funds to subsidize the honoraria, other benefits, uniforms and 
trainings of every barangay's roster of Barangay Tanods, we answer in the 
affirmative.

       Section 387 of the Local Government Code of 1991 expressly 
enumerated the main barangay officials in the barangay government, 
namely: the Punong Barangay, the seven (7) Sanggtmiang Barangay Members, 
the Barangay Treasurer, the Barangay Secretary, the SK Officials and the Lupong 
Tagapamayapa. The Barangay Tanods were not expressly mentioned 
therein. However, in a succeeding provision of the Local Government 
Code, specifically, Section 393 thereof, Barangay Tanods were already 
mentioned when said Section provides for the appointment of barangay 
tanod brigades, or their equivalent, which shall number not more that 
twenty (20) in each barangay. The first sentence of Section 393 further 
classified the Barangay Tanods as barangay officials.

       Furthermore, if the barangay deems it necessary to create additional 
positions in the barangay whose duties and functions are similar to that of 
the barangay tanods, the barangay concerned, by way of an ordinance, 
may create said positions pursuant to the second sentence of Section 387 
(b) of the Code, which empowered the barangay to "mot form community 
brigades and create such other positions or offices as may be 
deemed necessary to carry out the purposes of the barangay 
government in accordance with the needs of public service, subject

                                                           - 3 -

               to the budgetary limitations on personal services prescribed under 
               Title Five, Book H of this Code". Since these additional positions were 
               created through a barangay ordinance, the officials occupying these 
               positions are thus considered also as barangay officials.

                      In this regard, may we invite your attention to Section 393 (a) of the 
               Local Government Code of 1991, which provides and we quote:

                               "SECTION 393. Benefits of Barangay Officials.—
                      (a) Barangay officials includin barangay tanods and 
                      members of the lupong tagapamayapa, shall receive 
I,                    honoraria, allowances, and such other emoluments as 
                      may be authorized by law or barangay, municipal or city 
                      ordinance in accordance with the u revisions of this 
                      Code, but in no case shall it be less than One thousand 
                      pesos (P1,000.00) per month for the punong barangay 
                      and Six hundred pesos (P600.00) per month for the 
                      sangguniaug barangay members, barangay treasurer, and 
                      barangay secretary: Provided however That the annual 
                      ap ro riations for personal services shall be subject to 
                      the budgetary limitations • rescribed under Title Five 
                      Book II of this Code. (Emphasis Supplied)

                      Based on the foregoing, the City, by way of a city ordinance, may 
               allocate funds to subsidize the honoraria, allowances and such other 
               emoluments given to barangay tanods and equivalent brigades. The 
               foregoing provision may thus legally justify the allocation of city funds in 
               support of the project to standardize the Barangay Tanods' honoraria, 
               allowances and such other emoluments appurtenant to them as well as 
               their uniforms with paraphernalia and the conduct of seminars all aimed at 
               making them professional Barangay Tanods. May we take this opportunity, 
               however, to remind you that your proposed 
               standardizationiprofessionalization of Barangay Tanods should not, in any 
               way, remove from the punong barangay his power of operational control 
               and supervision over the Barangay Tanods.

                      We hope that we have addressed your concern accordingly.




                                                                                   Very truly yours,




                                                                              AUST RE A. PANADEll. 
                                                                                     UndersecretaT



               cc: Undersecretary Eduardo R. Solimari 
                    DiLG-NCR
                    LMP Bldg., Ermin Garcia St,
                    Cuban, Quezon City

               Legal/17

