                                                                                             Republic of the Philippi es
             DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR AND LOC GOVERNMENT
                                              Francisco Gold Condominium II, EDSA c r. Mapagmahal St. Diliman, Quezon Ci
  OFF11 OF THE UNDERSECRETARY FO                                                                                                                                           LOCAL GOVERNMENT

                                                                                                                                                                                                        'Vtr;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      06 September 2007


MR. ANICETO V. RASALAN 
Executive Assistant II
Office of the City Vice-Mayor 
Cotabato City

Dear Mr. Rasalan:

                       This has reference to your earlier lett r askit?g our opinion on the 
proper interpretation of the three-consecutiv term limit rule as embodied 
under Section 43 (b) of the Local Government ode of 1991 (RA 7160).

                       In your letter, you represented the folio mg facts:

                       ■          A Punong Barangay in the Province of Maguindanao was 
                                  already an incumbent barangay ch irman at the time the 
                                  Local Government Code of 1991 (RA 7160) t ok effect;

                       ■          In the 1994 barangay elections, he again ran as Punong 
                                  Barangay and won;

                       ■          In the 1995 national and local e ections, he filed his 
                                  certificate of candidacy as Muni !pal Vice-Mayor but, 
                                  unfortunately, he lost;

                        ■         In the 1997 barangay elections, e ag                                                                                                                         n ran for the
                                  position of Punong Barangay and w • n;

                        ■         He again sought for re-election for s id position in the 2002 
                                  barangay elections and won.

                        Hence, you now pose this query: s said elective barangay 
  official still eligible to run for re-election as Punong Barangay in 
  the forthcoming 2007 Synchronized Bar ngay and SK Elections?

                        Before dealing squarely with your que y, we                                                                                                                            eem it proper to give
  some discussions on the pertinent provisions                                                                                                                        of law applicable in the case
  at hand.

                                              "SEC. 43. Term of Office.- (•) The term of office 
                        of all local elective officials electe after the effectivity 
                        of this Code shall be three (3) year starting from noon 
                        of June 20, 1992 or such date as m• y be provided for by

                                          - 2 -


       law; except that of elective baran ray officials: 
       Provided, That all local officials first elected during the 
       local elections immediately following the ratification of 
       the 1987 Constitution shall serve until noon of June 30, 
       1992.


               (b) No local elective official shall serve for more
       than three () consecutive terms in the skime position. 
       Voluntary renunciation of the office for any length of
       time shall not be considered as an interruption in the        .    .
       continuity of service for the full term f r which the 
       elective official concerned was elected. xxx" (Emphasis 
       Supplied)


               (c) The term of office of bar             ngay officials and 
       member of the sangguniang kabata                  n shall be for three 
       (3) years, which shall begin after th             regular election of 
       barangay officials on the second Mo               day of 1994."


       The foregoing provision is the basi for the so-called three- 
consecutive term limit rule among local electiv officials, which disqualifies 
them from running for the same position after servin the same for three 
consecutive terms.


       In the leading case of Borja vs. COM              LEC (G.R. No. 133495, 03 
September 1998) and in several cases decided             hereafter up to the present, 
the Supreme Court consistently ruled that for             ection 43 (b) to apply, two 
(2) elements must concur, which are: (1) the I           cal official concerned must 
have been elected to that office; and (2) said I         cal official must have fully 
served the term of same office for three co               secut!ve terms. If these 
circumstances are present, then the concern               d local official is already 
disqualified to run for the same position                 on his supposed fourth
consecutive term.


       At this juncture, it is not amiss to point out that the aforequoted
Section 43 of the Local Government Code did               of expressly mandate that 
elective barangay officials are covered by               the three-term limit rule. 
However, the issue as to whether or not ele              tive bal rattgay officials are 
covered by the three-consecutive term limit rul            to hold the same position 
was finally put into rest when on 19 March 20             2, RA 9164 was approved, 
entitled: "An Act Providing for Sync                     ronized Barangay and 
Sangguniang Kabataan Elections, Ame                      ding Republic Act No. 
 7160, as amended, otherwise known as th                 • Loca Government Code 
of 1991, and For Other Purposes". Section                  thereof provides that:


               "The term of office of al barangay and 
        sangguniang kabataan officials aft r the effectivity of 
        this Act shat be three (3) years.


               No baran.gay elective official s r all srve for more 
        than three (3) consecutive terms in he same position: 
       Provided, however, That the term f office shall be 
        reckoned from the 1994 barangay el ctions. Voluntary






           tot

                                   - 3 -

      renunciation of office for any length of tir   e shall not be 
      considered as an interruption in the           continuity of 
      service for the full term for which the e     lective official
      was elected."

      As clearly provided for in the aforequoted provision, the first term of 
office of elective barangay officials, for purposes of computing the three- 
consecutive term limit rule, is to be reckoned from the 1994 barangay 
elections. It is of no moment, therefore, that the concerned elective 
barangay official was already a Punong Barangay at the time the Local 
Government Code took effect in 1992, since it is not included in the 
counting of the three-consecutive term. Important to note is the provision 
under Section 2 of RA 9164 as aforequoted providing that voluntary 
renunciation of office for any length of time shall not be considered as an 
interruption in the continuity of service for the full term for which the 
elective official was elected. Resignation is one instance where there is 
voluntary renunciation of an office by the elective local official concerned.

      After reading the set of facts, we noted that the controversial term of 
the Punong Barangay concerned is his term from 1994-1997. The 1997- 
2002 term has no issue because he was able to fully served the same, while 
the 2002 up to the present term, there is also no issue because he is still 
the incumbent Punong Barangay. Hence, the iss!..ie that is now posed 
before us for opinion is whether or not the term of office of the Punong 
Barangay concerned from 1994-1997 was considered interrupted in view of 
his filing of certificate of candidacy as Vice Mayor of the municipality in the 
1995 national and local elections.

      In reply thereto, we are of the view that the Punong Barangay 
concerned is no longer eligible to run for reelection the same position in 
the October 2007 barangay and SK electionS beca9se as to him, he has 
already served three-consecutive terms as Punong Barangay and thus, the 
prohibition will already attached when he will file a certificate of candidacy 
for the same office as Punong Barangay come October 2007 barangay 
elections.

      To explain our position, allow us first to discuss the legal effects of 
filing of certificate of candidacy. To start with, Section 67 of the Omnibus 
Election Code (BP 881) provides that "Any elective official whether 
national or local, running for any office other than the one which 
he is holding in a permanent capacity, except for President and 
 Vice-President, shall be considered ipso .factO resigned from his 
office upon filing of his certificate of candidacy" (Emphasis 
Supplied). However, this section was later on modified by Section 11 of 
Republic Act No. 8436, otherwise known as "An Act Authorizing the 
 Commission on Elections to Use an Automated Elections System in 
 the May 11, 1998 National and Local Elections and in Subsequent 
 National and Local Exercises", which provides that "xxx (a) any 
 elective official, whether national or local, running for any office 
 other than the one which he/she is holding in a permanent 
 capacity, except for president and vice-pres,nt, shall be deemed 
 resigned only upon the start of the campaign period corresponding 
 to the position for which he/she is running".

                                           - 4 -

       In a later development, the Fair Elections Act (RA 9006) was 
approved by the President of the Philippines on 12 February 2001, and 
Section 14 thereof expressly repealed Section 67 of the Omnibus Election 
Code and also rendered the 3rd paragraph of Section 11 of RA 8436 to be 
already ineffective. In view of the foregoing turn of events, there is now no 
law providing for the effects of filing of certificate of candidacy by 
incumbent elective officials whether running for the same or another office. 
Hence, at present, whether the elective local official would file a certificate 
of candidacy for the same or another office, he is not considered resigned.

       It becomes now relevant to study the legal effect when the subject 
Punong Barangay filed his certificate of candidacy in the 1995 national and 
local elections as Vice Mayor. At that time, the law effect was Section 67 
of the Omnibus Election Code. Accordingly, when h? filed his certificate of 
candidacy as Municipal Vice Mayor, which is a posit on other than the one 
he was then holding in a permanent capacity, which Was Punong Barangay, 
the legal effect was his automatic resignation, by operation of law from his 
position as Punong Barangay upon his filing of his certificate of candidacy 
as Vice Mayor. Consequently, since resignation is within the ambit of 
voluntary renunciation of the office, he is considered to have fully served 
his full term of 1994-1997 as Punong Barangay because the filing of his 
certificate of candidacy, which has the effect of his being resigned as 
Punong Barangay, shall not be considered as an interruption in the 
continuity of service for the full term for which he was elected in 1994 as 
Punong Barangay.

       We hope we have enlightened you on the matter.

                                                                  Very truly yours,




                                                              AUSTERE A. PANADERO 
                                                                    Undersecreta7
Legal:69:17

cc:    The Regional Director
       D1LG Regional Office No. 12 
       ARMM Complex, Cotabato City

