             Republic of the Philippines
   DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR AND LOCAL GOVERNMENT
          A. Francisco Qold Condominium II, EDSA 
         con Mapagmahal St., Diliman, Quezon City
OFFICE OF THE UNDERSECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT

                              26 April 2006


ATTY. MARKO S. LASERNA 
City Legal Officer
Santa Rosa City, Laguna

Dear Atty. Laserna:

   This pertains to your letter seeking our legal opinion on the following 
issues, to wit:

   1. Limitation on the exercise of the power to veto a Resolution as 
     provided in Section 55 of the Local Government Code;

   2. Whether or not the veto power vested in the Local Chief 
     Executive can be exercised by the Vice Mayor in his capacity as 
     Acting Mayor; and

   3. Whether or not the Vice Mayor acting as Mayor can veto 
     Resolution not involving a local development plan and public 
     investment program passed by the Sangguniang Panlungsod.

   In reply to the first issue, please be informed that generally, only 
ordinances are subject to veto by the Local Chief Executive. However, the Local  
Government Code allows the Local Chief Executive to veto resolutions when they 
deal with: (1) local development plans, or (2) public investment programs. The 
reason is that, resolutions of that kind involve the investment of public money; 
hence, are in the nature of ordinances (DILG Opinion No. 12, s. 1996). All other 
resolutions, i.e., those that do not involve local development plans or public 
investment programs need not be submitted to the Local Chief Executive for 
approval or subject to the veto power of the Local Chief Executive (DILG Opinion 
No. 118, s. 2003).

   Anent the second issue, we answer in the affirmative.

   Please be informed that Section 46 (a) of the Local Government Code 
provides that "when the governor, city or municipal mayor, or punong barangay

                    -2-

is temporarily incapacitated to perform his duties for physical or legal reason, 
such as, but not limited to, leave of absence, travel abroad and suspension from 
office, the vice governor, city or municipal vice mayor, or the highest ranking 
sangguniang barangay member shall automatically exercise the powers and 
perform the duties and functions of the local chief executive concerned, except the 
power to appoint, suspend, or dismiss employees which can only be exercised if 
the period of temporary incapacity exceeds thirty (30) working days".

    Please note that the law grants plenary power to the Vice Mayor as Acting 
Mayor as if it is the Mayor who is exercising such power, albeit such power was 
limited by the last sentence of the same provision. Such being the case, the 
Acting Mayor, who is temporarily assuming all the powers and performing all the 
functions of the Office of the Mayor, is endowed with the authority to approve or 
veto ordinances or the two kinds of resolutions stated above.

    With regard to the third issue, please be informed that as earlier stated, 
only resolutions which deal with local development plans or public investment 
programs are subject to the authority of the Mayor or the Acting Mayor for that 
matter, to either approve or veto the same. Conversely, all other resolutions are 
no longer subject to the said approval or veto power of the Mayor or even by the 
Vice Mayor in his capacity as Acting Mayor.

    Hope we have enlightened you on the matter.


                               Very truly yours,

                                  ri

                             NWE CELITO T. ANDANAR
                               Undersecret-

Legal:94.ins

cc: Director Roberto C. Abejero
    DILG Region IV-A
    Taguig City

