                                                1



               Republic of the Philippines
    DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR AND LOCAL GOVERNMENT
            A. Francisco (told Condominium II, EDSA 
            cor. Mapagmahal St., Diliman, Quezon City
OFFICE OF THE UNDERSECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT
                                        27
                                    06 June 2006


VICE MAYOR RODERICK A. ALCALA
City Hall, Lucena City 

Dear Vice Mayor Alcala:

    This refers to your request for this Department's legal opinion in 
connection with the action of the Sangguniang Panlungsod of Lucena City 
placing Acting Punong Barangay Rebecca S. Dator, through Resolution No. 
13-408 dated 10 April 2006, under preventive suspension for sixty (60) 
days, which Resolution was vetoed by the City Mayor.

    Culled from the records are the following:

❑ An administrative case was filed against Acting Punong Barangay Dator, 
  Barangay XI, that city, which was referred to the Committee on Laws, 
  Ethics and Barangay Affairs of the Sangguniang Panlungsod, for hearing;

❑ On 01 March 2006, the said Committee issued a report recommending 
  that the respondent Acting Punong Barangay Dator be placed under 
  preventive suspension;

❑ Adopting the said Committee report, the Sangguniang Panlungsod issued 
  the aforesaid Resolution and resolved to impose the preventive 
  suspension for sixty (60) days;

❑ However, the Mayor vetoed the said Sanggunian Resolution on the 
  ground that the power to impose preventive suspension resides in the 
  executive and not with the legislative.

    Such being the case, you have posed the following queries, to wit:

    1. Whether the veto message of the Honorable Ramon Y. 
      Talaga, Jr. is in order whereby it was alleged that the

                 -2-

    powers and authority to impose preventive suspension 
    against a barangay official is vested in the City Mayor and 
    not in the Legislative Body, the Sangguniang Panlungsod; 
    and

   2. Can the Committee on Accountability of Public Officials, 
    Ethics and Privileges where the said vetoed resolution was 
    recommitted pass a new resolution by merely recommending 
    to the City Mayor to suspend the OIC Barangay Official 
    concerned?"

   Before addressing your concerns, may we first settle the issue as to 
what actions of the Sangguniang Panlungsod are subject to the approval or 
veto of the City Mayor,

   Under the Local Government Code, the Sangguniang Panlungsod 
performs dual functions, namely: (1) legislative functions; and (2) quasi- 
judicial functions.

   Legislative functions pertain to the power of the Sangguniang 
Panlungsod to pass ordinances and resolutions. The pertinent provisions of 
the Code that govern these legislative functions of the Sangguniang 
Panlungsod are from Sections 48 to 59. On the other hand, quasi-judicial 
functions refer to the power of the Sangguniang Panlungsod to hear and 
decide administrative cases filed against elective barangay officials of the 
city. The pertinent provisions in the Code that pertains to the quasi-judicial 
functions of the Sangguniang Panlungsod are found from Sections 60 to 68 
thereof.

   In relation to its quasi-judicial functions, it is noted that the law 
constituted the Sangguniang Panlungsod as the disciplinary authority over 
elective barangay officials. On the other hand, pursuant to Section 32 of the 
Code, the City Mayor is the one vested by law the authority to exercise the 
power of general supervision over all its component barangays, including its 
officials, whether elective or appointive.

   Supervision has been defined by law as the power of the supervisor to 
oversee that laws are faithfully complied with by the subordinates. 
Therefore, to delineate the relationship between the Mayor and the elective 
barangay officials, on the one hand, from that of the Sangguniang

                 3

Panlungsod over the same officials, on the other, the Mayor is the one 
exercising the power of general supervision over all elective barangay 
officials, while the Sangguniang Panlungsod is the one exercising disciplinary  
authority over elective barangay officials.

   Examining now the power of the City Mayor to approve or veto 
measures enacted by the Sangguniang Panlungsod, it is evident from the 
provisions of the Local Government Code, particularly Sections 54 and 55 
thereof, that such power is available only with respect to measures passed 
by the Sanggunian pursuant to its legislative functions. On the other hand, a 
reading of Sections 60-68 of the same Code would reveal that nothing 
therein requires the approval by the City Mayor of, or allows him to veto any 
measure passed by the Sanggunian in the exercise of its quasi-judicial 
functions.

   For emphasis, and as a matter of illustration, Section 66 of the Code 
provides for the manner by which the Sanggunian shall render its decision in 
its quasi-judicial functions. Nothing therein provides that the decision of the 
Sangguniang Panlungsod in administrative cases is subject to the approval of 
the City Mayor. Hence, it is clear that decisions of the Sangguniang 
Panlungsod in disposing administrative cases against elective barangay 
officials are not anymore subject to the approval, or for that matter, veto of  
the City Mayor. The reason for this is quite clear in the Code when it vested 
solely to the Sangguniang Panlungsod the power to hear and decide 
administrative cases against elective barangay officials. One may, however, 
wonder why under Section 63 of the Code, it is so provided that a 
preventive suspension is to be imposed by the Mayor. It is our considered 
position, as elucidated in DILG Opinion No. 44, s. 2004 (copy of which is 
hereto attached for reference) that while the power to determine as to 
whether or not the respondent should be placed under preventive suspension 
lies with the Sangguniang Panlungsod, the matter of imposition, however, is 
given to the Mayor considering that at that point in time, the respondent 
elective barangay official is still presumed innocent there being no decision 
yet in the administrative case, such that the preventive suspension has to be 
imposed by the Mayor being the supervisor of the concerned elective 
barangay official.

   May we take this opportunity of clarifying the role of the Sangguniang 
Panlungsod vis-à-vis the City Mayor with respect to the imposition of 
preventive suspension. Although there is no Supreme Court ruling yet, there





                                   Ai

                    -3-

was already a Court of Appeals ruling in the case of Matugas vs. Judge 
Buyser and Mayor Navarro (CA-G.R. SP No. 5560) where the Court of 
Appeals had the occasion to rule, in gist, that the determination of whether 
to place the respondent under preventive suspension or not, is with the 
Sanggunian. And once the Sanggunian directs the Mayor to impose the 
preventive suspension, it becomes ministerial on his part to impose the 
same.

    Foregoing considered, with regard to the first issue, we are of the 
view that the Mayor's veto of such Sanggunian resolution imposing the 
preventive suspension upon the respondent Acting Punong Barangay, is 
bereft of any legal basis since said Resolution was issued by the 
Sangguniang Panlungsod in furtherance to its quasi-judicial functions.

    With regard to the second issue, we see no necessity for the 
Committee on Accountability of Public Officials, Ethics and Privileges to pass 
a new resolution recommending to the City Mayor to preventively suspend 
the concerned respondent barangay official. What should be done instead is 
for the Sangguniang Panlungsod to come up with another resolution asking 
the City Mayor to implement its previous resolution by imposing the 60-day 
preventive suspension against said respondent barangay official, as it is one 
of his functions and duties under Section 63 of the Local Government Code.

    We hope we have enlightened you on the matter.


                              Very truly yours,


                                 L.,
                            WE CELITO T. ANDANAR. 
                               Undersecretary_ e/

Legalp7/La

cc: Director Roberto C. Abejero
    DILG Region IV-A
    Calderon Bldg., EDSA
    Diliman, Quezon City

