                                            Republic of the Philippi          es
                DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR AND                                OCAL gOVERNMENT
                                   A. Francisco Gold Condominium              II Bldg, EDSA 
                                 corner Mapagrnahal St., Diliman,             uezon C ty

                                OFFICE OF THE UNDERSE RETARY
                                                                                      44u;                       _a— 214 
                                                                         March 3. 2008

Vice-Mayor Aristotle J. Gaza 
Office of the S anggun iang Bayan 
Hermosa, Bataan

Dear Vice-Mayor Gaza:

          This pertains to your letter seeking our legal opinion regarding the Amended 
provision of your Internal Rules and Procedures under Rule IV, Section 1 which 
provides:

                     "Section 1(j). To relinquish the chai - to the presiding Officer 
          Pro-Temporc, or in the latter's absence, to any member of the 
          Sanggunian who shall act as Temporary Pr-siding Officer. He may 
          also relinquish the chair in order to particil ate in the deliberation of 
          the body."

          Said amendment was undertaken by your cot tied usi Ig as reference and guide 
the Department's Legal Opinion No. 85, dated May 9, 1998 rendered to Vice-Mayor 
Amelia S. Navarri.. City Hall, Santiago City, on the ssue of whether or not the Vice- 
Mayor can relinquish his seat as the Presiding Officer in the Saugguniang Bayan to join 
in the parliamentar\ debate as member thereof

          However, during your orientation seminar in he Development Academy of the 
                 different opinion was rendered when the score pet y was raised.

          In this regard, you would now like to seek th legal c                          pinion of the _Department
regarding the validity of the amended provisions.

          In reply thereto, please be advised, that in else of inconsistency between the 
DILG Opinion and the discussion in the seminar, the DILL Opinion shall prevail being 
the official pronouncement of the Department. Hence, the amended provision of Internal 
rules and procedures adopted {-y the sangguniang yan of Hermosa particularly Rule 
IV, Section 1(.0) is in order.




                                                                         A STERE A. PANA1Ok0
                                                                                  Lind -rsecr   eLai\-
 s,"Alintil

