;'







                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             Republic of the Philippines 
                  1                                                                                   DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR AND LOCAL GOVERNMENT                                                                            Francisco Gold Condominium 11 Bkhz„ EDSA 
                                                                                                                                                                                                                corner Mapao;mahal Street, Diliman. Quezon City

                                               OFFICE OF TINE UNDERSECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT



                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    June 30, 2008

                                               MAYOR WILMA DAM" HILLMAN 
                                               Castillejos, Zambales

                                               Dear Mayor Billman:

                                                                                                          This pertains to your letter seeking our legal opinion on the proper application 
                                               and interpretation of the three (3) consecutive term limit rule of elective local officials 
                                               to hold the same position.

                                                                                                               Per your letter, your first term was on May 14, 2001. However, an election 
                                               protest was lodged by your contender Enrique Magsaysay. The Regional Trial Court of 
                                               Olongapo City ruled in his favor and issued a decision on May 7, 2002. Magsaysay then 
                                               acted in the manner of a truly elected Mayor from May 21, 2002 to July 30, 2004. 
                                               Accordingly, your appeal to the Commission on Election upheld your proclamation but 
                                               you were not able to assume office because Magsaysay never handed to you the seat 
                                               and was able to secure a Temporary Restraining Order from the Supreme Court. Hence, 
                                               you only served eleven months in your first term.

                                                                                                               In the May 2004 national and local elections, you ran again and won. 
                                               Consequently, your contender Jose Angelo Dominguez filed a petition before the 
                                               COMELEC, whereupon the first division thereof, issued a resolution on July 14, 2004 
                                               which annulled your proclamation. The vice mayor assumed office from February 16, 
                                               2006 to March 31, 2006. Again, you filed an appeal to the COMELEC, which in turn 
                                               decided to conduct a recount and the result of the recount was favorable to you. 
                                               Accordingly, you assumed office from April 1, 2006 until the expiration of your term on 
                                               May of 2007.

                                                                                                               During the 114 May 2007 national and local elections, you were reelected as
                                               Mayor.

                                                                                                               Based on the facts given, you now seek our legal opinion regarding the following 
                                               issues, which we quo{e to wit:

                                                                                                                                                                             "1) Does the term which you were not able to serve, 
                                                                                                               counts?

                                                                                                               term, which means you are still eligible to run for the       2) Whether or not your term in 2007 considered a first 
                                                                                                               remaining two terms?"

          nN  ry
          I





                                                                                                -2-


                                     In reply thereto, please be informed that questions one and two are related, 
                         hence, they may be answered jointly,


                                     May we invite your attention to Section 43 (b) of the Local Government Code, 
                         which we hereunder quote:


                                                  "No elective official shall serve for more than three (3) 
                                     consecutive terms in the same position. Voluntary renunciation of 
                                     the office for any length of time shall not be considered as an 
                                     interruption in the continuity of service for the full term which the 
                                     elective official concerned was elected."


          ii                       ' In the leading case of Borja vs. COMELEC (G.R. No. 133495, 03 September 1998) 
                         and in several 'cases decided thereafter up to the present, the Supreme Court 
                         consistently ruled that for Section 43 (b) to apply where a local elective official is 
                         disqualified to run for the same position after serving the said position for three 
                         consecutive terms, two (2) elements must concur, which are: (1) the local official 
                         concerned must have been duly elected to that office; and (2) said local official must 
                         have fully served tnat same office for three consecutive terms. if these circumstances 
                         are present, then the concerned local official is already disqualified to run for the same 
                         position in the supposed fourth consecutive term.


                                     Applying this now to your case, we are of view that your first and second terms 
                         should not be counted as one full term each considering that you have not fully served 
                         your term of office. This is so because the second element as mentioned in the 
                         immediately preceding paragraph is not present. Clearly from your narration of facts, 
                         you were not able to fully serve the full term of your office in your supposed first and 
                         second terms. It bears to note that in your supposed first term, you only served for 
                         eleven (11) months and in your supposed second term in 2004 elections, you only 
                         assumed office from April 2006 until the expiration of your term on May 2007. Hence, 
                         the continuity of your service for your supposedly first and second terms were 
;'                       intthupted. In this connection, please note that section 43 (b) of the code mentioned 
                         "three (3) consecutive terms in the same position," Consecutive means no interruption.


                                     With regard to your second query, please be informed that for purposes of 
                         counting the three consecutive term, your first term for the same position should be 
                         reckoned from noon of 30 June 2007, which is the commencement of your term in 
                         relation to the 2007 May election.


                                      We hope we have enlightened you on the matter.
   I •


                                                                                                                                   Very truly yours,






                                                                                                                           AUSTERE A. PANADEr
          i,    I                                                                                                                        Undersecretary


fIE                       Leg91:941cga

          ;
          I

