                  REPUBLIC OF THE PHILIPPINES 
        DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR AND LOCAL GOVERNMENT 
           Francisco Gold Condominium II, EDSA cor. Mapagmahal St., 
                      Diliman, Quezon City


               OFFICE OF THE UNDERSECRETARY lit t ovi '61 t'4 2001_

                                      October 25, 2006



VICE MAYOR RUSSEL G. PLEYTO 
Sta. Maria, Bulacan

Dear Vice Mayor Pleyto:

     This refers to your letter inquiring on whether or not resolutions of the Sangguniang 
Bayan approving reviewed barangay ordinances/resolutions are subject to the veto power of the 
Municipal Mayor.

     In reply thereto please be informed that actions of the Sangguniang Panlungsod or 
Sangguniang Bayan in the exercise of its review power per Section 57 of RA 7160, over 
approved ordinances or resolutions of the Barangay would no longer require the approval of the 
municipal mayor because his power to approve or disapprove legislative measures of the 
Sangguniang Bayan pertains only to those that were enacted by the Sangguniang Bayan of his 
municipality. The power to review barangay ordinances, as could be clearly seen from Section 
57 of the Local Government Code, is lodged solely to the Sanggunian Bayan.

     Such being the case, your practice of submitting to the mayor your sangguniang 
resolution approving or disapproving a barangay ordinance as consequence of the review power 
of the Sangguniang Bayan under Section 57 of the Local Government Code is considered a mere 
surplusage of procedure as the same is not even required by the Local Government Code.

     We hope that we have enlightened you on the matter.



                                      Very truly yours,




                                  "NCELITO T. ANDANA)t 
                                       Undersecretary it6 

Cc:  Dir. Josephine Castilla-Go
     DILG Regional Office No. 3 
     San Fernando City, Pampanga

Legal:vinz:ins

